<section id="Grids">
<title>Background Color or Image</title>

<para>
By default, Multigraph draws a solid white background behind every graph.
You can specify an alternate background color, and or an image to be used
in the background of a graph, via the <sgmltag>background</sgmltag> tag.
The <sgmltag>background</sgmltag> tag, if it is present at all, should appear
at the top level of the &Mugl; file, inside the <sgmltag>&mugl;</sgmltag> tag.
It accepts a single optional attribute:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>color</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The color to use for the graph background.  The default is white
("0xffffff").
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>
The
<sgmltag>img</sgmltag> subtag, which may optionally appear inside the
<sgmltag>background</sgmltag> tag, can be used to specify an image to
be drawn in the background.  It accepts the following attributes:
</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>src</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The URL of the image to be used.  This URL may be either relative (to the location of the Multigraph SWF file), or
absolute.  If it is on a different server from the Multigraph SWF file, the normal constraints of Flash security
apply (i.e. access must be allowed by a crossdomain file on the server containing the image).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>anchor</sgmltag></term></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>base</sgmltag></term></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>position</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
These attributes specify where the background image should be drawn in the graph, according
to the conventions described in <xref linkend="Positioning"/>.
<sgmltag>base</sgmltag> is the location of the base point relative to
either the padding box or the plot area (the default is the padding box; see
the 
<sgmltag>frame</sgmltag> attribute below); 
the default value for <sgmltag>base</sgmltag> is "-1 -1" --- i.e. the upper left corner.
The default for <sgmltag>anchor</sgmltag> is also "-1 -1", which means that the upper left
corner of the image is anchored to the base point.
<sgmltag>position</sgmltag> is a coordinate pair of pixel offsets, as described in
<xref linkend="Positioning"/>; its default value is "0 0".
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><sgmltag>frame</sgmltag></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The <sgmltag>frame</sgmltag> attribute determines whether the background image
is positioned relative to the plot area or the padding box (described in <xref linkend="BordersMarginsPlotArea"/>).
More precisely, it determines the coordinate system of the <sgmltag>base</sgmltag> point, 
described above.
The default value is "padding", which means that the background image will be positioned relative
to the padding area (the entire part of the graph that is inside the border).
If you want to position the background image relative to just the plot area, however,
you can specify "plot" for the <sgmltag>frame</sgmltag>
attribute, in which case the base point will refer to the plot area.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>



</section>
